<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the nature of faith. A sermon, / by Barten Holyday, Doctor of Divinity.</title>
            <author>Holyday, Barton, 1593-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86493</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2532</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E809_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207573</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866616</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866616</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118893</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86493)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118893)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 123:E809[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the nature of faith. A sermon, / by Barten Holyday, Doctor of Divinity.</title>
                  <author>Holyday, Barton, 1593-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S.G. for W. Lee, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Turks Head in Fleetstreet, over against Fetter-lane end.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "September. 5th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews XI, 4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118893:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OF THE NATURE OF FAITH.</p>
            <p>A SERMON, BY <hi>BARTEN HOLYDAY,</hi> Doctor of Divinity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. G.</hi> for <hi>W. Lee,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the <hi>Turks Head</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> over againſt <hi>Fetter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane</hi> end. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:118893:2"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEBR. 11.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>By Faith <hi>Abel</hi> offered unto God a more excellent ſacrifice then <hi>Cain.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118893:2"/>
            <head>OF The Nature of <hi>FAITH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is not any action in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon life performed without a kinde of belief: no man of a rectified reaſon under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking any buſineſs, but with a belief both of the poſſibility of it, and of the benefit. Which as it is true even of civil faith in outward life, ſo is it much more true of true faith in the inward life. For without this no man can pleaſe God; no man can intend to pleaſe God. He that comes to God muſt believe that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſeek him. Faith then muſt be the beginning of our action; and ſhould have been the beginning of <hi>Cain's</hi> action, as it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118893:3"/>was of <hi>Abels;</hi> but as at firſt it made an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward difference between their perſons, ſo at laſt an outward alſo between their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices. But the more diſtinctly to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the actions of theſe brothers, we may diſtinctly view the ſacrificers; the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices; the difference, and the cauſe of the difference, which was Faith; by faith <hi>Abel</hi> offered unto God a more excellent ſacrifice then <hi>Cain.</hi> Behold the perſons, <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel.</hi> The firſt work that God performed for man, was to make him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: and the firſt work that man perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med after God's work, was to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf imperfect. Which when <hi>Adam</hi> had done, and afterwards had children, God, in his wiſdome, did in his firſt childe <hi>Cain</hi> ſhew him his graceleſs ſtate into which he was fallen; as in his mercy he did in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſon <hi>Abel</hi> ſhew him, in ſome propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the good eſtate into which he was reſtored. In which two brothers God was pleaſed to ſhew that diviſion which afterwards ſucceeded in mankinde; <hi>Abel</hi> being the firſt of the moſt eminently righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and <hi>Cain</hi> the firſt of the notoriouſly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118893:3"/>wicked. Which difference in their inward eſtate, ſome think to have been ſhadowed out in their outward eſtate. Which ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may not be admitted for truth, both their profeſſions being lawful; though in ſome degree it may be granted, if we look upon the occaſions and readineſs of treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs in the condition of the one, more then of the other. Behold, <hi>Gain</hi> minding earthly things, to be ſure of his portion, betakes himſelf to gainful husbandry and covetous commerce, and with his ſon <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> builds a City; invents alſo, as the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Joſepbus</hi> tells us, weights and meaſures; and takes poſſeſſion of the Eaſtern parts, making himſelf a Lord in the earth, which he choſe for his portion: though we muſt farther cenſure it as a woful husbandry, to water the earth with his brothers blood, and then to plow it. But behold, <hi>Abel</hi> a Shepherd, the holy Patriarch of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, and the Princes of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Behold, a condition of life excellent for ſimplicity, being a ſtranger, or rather an enemy to City-craft. Behold, a life, that does not ſo take up the minde, as not to reſpite it to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118893:4"/>meditation, &amp; the true uſe of life; to medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the works of God, &amp; ſo of our ſelvs a chief work of God. Behold, a life, that requires not the fixed glory of an habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but aptly expreſſing by its moveable ſhelter the humble pilgrimage of our life. Behold, a life helping us in this life with the ready charity and wiſdom of clothing. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, a life, which in that firſt age he help'd them to the matter of their ſacrifice, and was truly the ſubſtance of it, whiles the embleme of the due innocency of it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, a life, not onely innocent, but emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, a life that is the life, whiles the live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly image of a Prince and of God; a good ruler being the Shepherd of his people, careful to guide them, careful to preſerve them; not letting the ſheers go deeper then the wooll. Behold, a life, the image of God, tender in his providence over the improvident ſheep; more tender in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence over man; moſt tender in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence over innocent men, his Church; and therefore anciently the Shepherd was not ſo joyfully clothed with the fleece, as Kings, and the King of Kings with the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118893:4"/>comfort and honorable title of the Shepherds of the people. Now theſe two brothers did not onely differ thus in profeſſion, but alſo ſucceſſion. <hi>Cain</hi> had wealth and iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue; a father he was, though of a race, that was not ſo happy, as to degenerate. But <hi>Abel</hi> had the excellencies of ſanctity and martyrdome. Succeſſion he had none, but his example: and in reſpect of age, in that age of the world, he died yong; prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the growing danger of corruption by grave and death. Yet after an excellent manner God gave ſucceſſion unto <hi>Abel,</hi> whiles in ſtead of <hi>Abel</hi> he gave to <hi>Adam</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious <hi>Seth:</hi> whoſe righteous poſterity dealing in innocent arts, did afterwards dwell in the holy Land; the type of that inheritance, at which they aimed- Nor were their poſterities diſtinguiſhed only in conditions, but alſo in name; the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male poſterity of <hi>Cain</hi> (as ſome tell us) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called the daughters of men; as the male poſterity of <hi>Abel</hi> ſupplied in <hi>Seth,</hi> and which were taken with thoſe beauties, are for their worthy deſcent, though not for their frailtie, called the ſons of God.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118893:5"/>Theſe then being the conditions of the perſons, you may ſee, yea, fore-ſee the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of their ſacrifices; for each of them did offer unto God a <hi>ſacrifice.</hi> The end of the creature is the honour of the Creator; and ſuch honor is to be performed by ſome acknowledgement; and ſuch acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment has been always made by ſacrifice: which, as it is due unto God by the right of Creation, ſo has it been always perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med unto God from the time of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And ſuch duty being required of man by God, God always inſtructed man with ſuch knowledge, whereby he ſhould be able to perform ſuch duty. In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world, God taught <hi>Adam,</hi> and in proceſs of times, <hi>Adam</hi> taught <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> both the kinde and manner of their ſacrifice. Before and under the Law, the ſacrifices were much of a like nature, they being both external; and yet they differed by the many and ſpecial rites and ceremonies uſed in ſacrifice under the Law. The <hi>Moſaical ſacrifices</hi> were of three kindes: ſome of them being divided, part unto God, part to the Prieſt, and part to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118893:5"/>the people: ſuch was the peace-offering, and this offering was the meaneſt. Some of them were divided, part unto God, and part to the Prieſt: ſuch was the ſinne-of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and this was the ſecond beſt. But the laſt was the burnt-offering, which was offered onely unto God, and this was the moſt excellent. Now all the ſacrifices be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law were like unto this, being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered all onely unto God: as all the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſacrifices now under the Goſpel, as Love, Prayer, Faſting, Obedience, Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Thankfulneſs, and the like, into which thoſe external ſacrifices were changed by Chriſt, are all offered only unto God. And indeed even in thoſe firſt ſacrifices, the end being to unite man unto God, <hi>ut ſancta ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate illi adhaereamus,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks; there was not onely the external part, but alſo the inward, that with which it was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, the affection; of which the outward was but a ſign. Without which mind, God told them by his Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> He that kills an Oxe, is as if he ſlew a man: he that ſacrifices a Lamb, as if he cut off a dog's neck: he that offers an oblation, as if he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118893:6"/>offered ſwine's blood: he that burns in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, as if he bleſſed an idol. <hi>Non ſacrificia ſunt quae ſanctificant, ſed gratia offerentis,</hi> ſayes <hi>Irenaeus;</hi> The holineſs is not in the ſacrifice, but in the ſacrificer. It is not ſaid, that God had reſpect to <hi>Abel's</hi> ſacrifice, but to <hi>Abel</hi> and his ſacrifice; to ſignifie, as ſome think, that God looked firſt upon his faith, and afterwards on his ſacrifice. Indeed the very Heathen underſtand this Divinity. <hi>Plato</hi> tells us, that the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> having with exceſſive ſacrifices implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Jupiter Ammon</hi> in a war againſt the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemonians,</hi> yet receiving the overthrow, ſent Embaſſadors to expoſtulate the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with their God, who was ſhrewdly ſhent by them, and asked, how chance he failed them in this their enterpriſe? to whom their God excuſed himſelf by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that indeed he acknowledged, their Altars were better dreſſed then the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians;</hi> but that nothing was dreſſed but their Altars, or that their Altars were better dreſſed then their mindes. The minde then being required in a true ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, you may view the ſacrifices of <hi>Cain</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118893:6"/>and <hi>Abel:</hi> who, according to the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions they had from <hi>Adam,</hi> bring their ſacrifices from their own profeſſions; at the end of days, (<hi>Gen.</hi> 4.3.) that is, in proceſſe of time. Which ſome think to have been at the yeer's end; then indeed men were wont ſolemnly to ſacrifice to God in thankfulneſſe, having gathered in their fruits. So did the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards command, <hi>Exodus</hi> 23.16. which order was obſerved from the beginning by the Fathers, and as the Philoſopher in his <hi>Morals</hi> tells us, it was obſerved even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Gentiles. But with the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of old, there was beſides a Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to God, a yearly remembrance alſo of their ſinnes, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.3. and a hope of the forgiveneſſe of them by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to come; the Legall ſacrifices being inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.1, 2. Now ſome more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly think, theſe brothers offered theſe ſacrifices, by the hand of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Adam;</hi> who was High Prieſt, (as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ordinarily the firſt-born in fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies were Prieſts until <hi>Moſes</hi>) and that he offered their gifts upon an altar. <hi>Cain,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118893:7"/>an Husbandman brought of the fruit of the ground; and <hi>Abel,</hi> being a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, brought of the firſtlings of his flock, and of the fat thereof. Theſe were their ſacrifices, but <hi>Abel</hi> offered the more excellent ſacrifice; this was the <hi>difference</hi> of the ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>That it was better, it may partly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from the ſacrifice it ſelf; for whereas it is onely ſaid, (<hi>Gen.</hi> 4.3.) <hi>Cain</hi>'s was of the fruit of the ground; the holy Ghoſt more accurately (<hi>Gen</hi> 4.4.) deſcribes <hi>Abels</hi> to have been of the firſtlings of his flock, and the fat thereof. Which was even ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the minde of God, to whom the firſt born were the moſt acceptable of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and ſuch as afterwards he preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by <hi>Moſes.</hi> And as for the offering of the fat, that likewiſe was as acceptable; whether by that be ſignified the fatteſt of his flock; or whether he brought the fat and burnt it to the Lord, as God did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards command by <hi>Moſes,</hi> figuratively im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, that the hardneſſe of the heart is to be conſum'd by the fireof the Spirit, as ſome devoutly conceive; though without
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118893:7"/>doubt it properly ſignifies the excellency of the ſacrifice; and but in an after-ſenſe want of ſenſe, and unbelief. Again, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel's</hi> ſacrifice was the better, it may appear from Gods approbation of it, it being ſaid, that God had reſpect to <hi>Abel</hi> and to his offering, but unto <hi>Cain</hi> and his offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring he had not reſpect. God <hi>had reſpect to Abel's</hi> offering, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>(&amp; reſpexit)</hi> which ſignifies to look upon a thing with inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiveneſs and approbation, and ſo with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: ſo that God delighted in <hi>Abels</hi> ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; which pleaſure of the Lord is ſomtimes call'd <hi>ſeeing:</hi> ſo God is ſaid to have <hi>reſpect,</hi> or to <hi>ſee Abels</hi> offering: and ſometimes it is called <hi>ſmelling;</hi> as it is ſaid of <hi>Noah's</hi> firſt ſacrifice after the flood: <hi>The Lord ſmelled a ſweet ſavour, Gen.</hi> 8.21. So in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.19. When it is ſaid, Let the Lord <hi>accept</hi> an offering, the Margin from the Original renders it, Let him <hi>ſmell</hi> an offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Laſtly, that it was better, God teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, no doubt, by ſome outward ſigne; for otherwiſe how could <hi>Cain</hi> have known, that God accepted not his offering, and ſo fall into into diſcontent? And this ſign as Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> (in his <hi>Hebraical</hi> Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118893:8"/>tells us, was no other then Fire ſent down upon the ſacrifice of <hi>Abel,</hi> which it conſumed, leaving <hi>Cain's</hi> untouched. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which ſenſe <hi>Theodoſian</hi> renders it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, God fir'd <hi>Abel</hi> and his ſacrifice. And this is moſt probable, ſince God did afterwards in that manner declare his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and acceptance of other mens ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. As of the ſacrifice at <hi>Aarons</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, <hi>Levit.</hi> 9.24. Of <hi>Gideons</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>Judg.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 21. Of <hi>Davids,</hi> 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.26. Of <hi>Solomons,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.1. Of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liahs</hi> alſo, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.38. Nay, the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens falſe Deity (the Devil) by divine permiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, did thus deal by the ſacrifices of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered amongſt them; <hi>Solinus</hi> telling us, <hi>A litato numine fit incendium;</hi> They brought the ſacrifice, and the God brought the fire, which was according to a permitted imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods work; who teſtified his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable acceptance of a ſacrifice, by <hi>turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to aſhes:</hi> ſo prayes the Church for <hi>Davids</hi> offering, (according to the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20.3. Thus we ſee, that <hi>Abel's</hi> was the more excellent ſacrifice: but now we muſt know, <hi>why</hi> it vvas the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent: we ſee the difference, now vvee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118893:8"/>muſt ſee the <hi>cauſe</hi> of the difference: and the Apoſtle tells us it was <hi>Faith, by Faith.</hi> If the Apoſtle had not here ſtaid our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, vvee might have embraced the fine conjecture of <hi>Joſephus:</hi> a conjecture ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though not found. He vvill have the diverſity to ariſe from the diverſity of their profeſſions. <hi>Abel's</hi> ſacrifice being taken out of his flock, a ſacrifice provided to his hand in the ſimplicity of nature: but <hi>Cain's</hi> being a ſacrifice from the fruit of the earth, vvhich he did dreſſe vvith much care and covetouſneſſe, forcing it by art unto abundance; and ſo a ſacrifice of guilt and violence. But this caus does as much differ from the true cauſe, as <hi>Cain's</hi> ſacrifice diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Abel's:</hi> it does as much differ, though not as odiouſly, the fruits of the earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſacrifice afterwards alſo, (as appears, <hi>Lev.</hi> 23.14.) but <hi>Cains</hi> was vvithout faith, as <hi>Abel's,</hi> the more excellent being offer'd by Faith. God, ſaith <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> look'd upon <hi>Abel's</hi> ſacrifice, and not upon <hi>Cain's, propter ingenium offerentium, Qualis eſt enim erga De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um voluntas offerentis, talis eſt erga oblationem voluntas Dei;</hi> ſuch as is the ſacrificers wil to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118893:9"/>God, ſuch is God's vvill towards the ſacrifice. That therefore we may fully underſtand the nature of his offering, we muſt fully underſtand the nature of his Faith; and then we may be able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and imitate <hi>Abel's</hi> devotion in his ſacrifice, which he offered by Faith. Know then we muſt, that whatſoever creature is indued with reaſon, the ſame is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo made capable of a faith: all faith preſuppoſing reaſon, in which it is implan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in which it is employed. Thus is there a faith in the glorious Angels, who are indued with analogical reaſon, and believe in God, that they ſhall be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, with perſeverance in which faith, they perſevere in their perfection. You ſhall ſee a faith too in the wicked Angels, who do not onely know Gods Word, but alſo give aſſent unto ſuch knowledge: which yet proceeds not from any ſpecial illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but from the remainder of their natural angelical knowledge ſince their fall. You ſhall finde a faith too in wicked men: a faith, by which they ſhall not ſave, but continue and condemn themſelves.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118893:9"/>Yet by this faith, they ſhall not onely know, and aſſent unto Gods word, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo profeſſe that knowledge and aſſent; as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> teſtifies of <hi>Simon Magus, Acts</hi> 8.13. To which degree the Devils alſo in ſome ſort arrive; for they confeſſed, that Chriſt was the Sonne of the moſt High; and yet looked for no ſalvation by him: nay, they diſclaimed all ſalvation by him, crying out, What have we to do with thee? You ſhall yet finde a greater faith in wicked men; whereby they ſhall not onely know and aſſent, and profeſſe; but alſo rejoice, nay, and bring forth fruit. Surely this will make the juſt man fear; this will make him begin to ſuſpect him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and not onely reſt content with a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect faith, to believe; but ſeek alſo for a reflexive faith to believe, that he does be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. Yet even the faith of the wicked ſhall be attended with joy, it ſhall be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with fruit. They ſhall bear fruit, but it ſhall be like corn on the houſe-top; in the heat of Summer it ſhall wither. They ſhall bear fruit, but it ſhall be like ſeed in the ſtony ground; it ſhall take no deep
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118893:10"/>root, (<hi>Luke</hi> 8.13.) This faith ſhall paſſe away with time, it ſhall paſſe away like time, the cauſes of it ſhall paſſe away; er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, profit, glory, which commonly are the true cauſes of falſe faith. Nay, ye ſhall finde a greater faith even in wicked men; a faith able to work miracles; which faith where it has been found, is judged to have been commonly grounded on ſome revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or on ſome promiſe of God: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a man believes God will bring ſuch things to paſſe by him, as by an inſtrument of ſuch miracles. And this was the faith which <hi>Simon Magus</hi> would have bought of the Apoſtles, (<hi>Acts</hi> 8.19.) and though he could not get it for his money, yet a worſe hypocrite had it freely; even <hi>Judas</hi> the worſt of reprobates. Yea, and many more ſhall have part in this faith, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſhall have no part in Chriſt; nay, when at the laſt day, they ſhall ſay to our Saviour, Lord, in thy name we have caſt out Devils, they ſhall be returned with I know you not. They ſhall be caſt out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe Devils, whom once in his name they themſelves caſt out. And may not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118893:10"/>this ſhake even the elect? May not this caſt them into doubting of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation? Surely it may, ſurely it does; but it is but at ſome times; it is but for ſome time; it is but in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, ſhake them it does: but it is as the mighty wind ſhakes a mighty Tree: it does but ſhake it, it overthrow's it not; nay, it is ſo farre from overthrowing of it, that by the ſhaking of it, it makes it take the deeper root: whiles both the tender ſtrings, and alſo the firmer and hidden ſpurres by which it is faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, do by the hollowing of the earth, pierce farther into the earth. Thus does the righteous man, vvhen he ſees, that Faith even in a wicked man may be atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vvith profeſſion, joy, fruit, nay, with miracles: it does not make him deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, but diligent; diligent to trie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by the rules delivered in Gods Word, to ſee whether or no hee have ſaving Faith: Which indeed may more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, more effectually, be called the Faith of miracles, it being the trueſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, that any thing ſhould be found in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118893:11"/>man, which ſhould be able to be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible inſtrument of the ſalvation of man. Yet ſuch is Faith, the Faith of the elect: who therefore carefully ask coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſail of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> to know, what ſuch Faith is; who has more carefully taught us, what ſuch Faith is. And he has taught us, that it is, The ſubſtance of things ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for, the evidence of things not ſeen, (<hi>Hebrews</hi> 11.1.) By which we may learn both the nature of the things, which our Faith aims at, and alſo the nature of our Faith it ſelf. The things which Faith aims at, have a twofold nature: they are things not as yet in our poſſeſſion; they are things not as yet in our ſight: for in this life they are but hoped for, and in this life they are inviſible. Now Faith is of that nature, that it ſupplies both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: for by Faith vve have even here a kinde of poſſeſſion; and by Faith wee have even here a kinde of ſight. It is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, the foundation, the ground, the confidence, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſubſiſtence; it is that, by which things that are but hoped for, are in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118893:11"/>manner in our poſſeſſion already. It is the evidence of things not ſeen: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the argument, proof, demonſtration; S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> renders it the <hi>conviction</hi> of things not ſeen. For as in natural knowledge, Reaſon does convince the underſtanding, ſo in ſupernatural knowledge Faith does convince the underſtanding; not by the manifeſtation of the thing it ſelf, but by the authority of God, that ſays it. By which authority, as the Apoſtle ſays, he brings into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt, (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5.) And it is of things not ſeen; <hi>Quae enim apparent</hi> (ſayes Saint <hi>Gregory) jam fidem non habent, ſed agnitionem.</hi> It is not ſo proper to ſay, we believe things, that are preſent, as to ſay, we acknowledge them. By Faith then we have a kinde of poſſeſſion of all thoſe glories, which we now but hope for; and by Faith we may be ſaid, even to ſee thoſe glories, which in this life cannot be ſeen. This is the nature of Faith, which even the meaneſt may apprehend; and if the more ſubtle would farther view it, they may from inquiſitiver eaſon improved
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118893:12"/>by Religion know, That it is an habit of the underſtanding, whereby eternal life is begun in us, making the underſtanding firmly aſſent to things, that do not appear: It is an <hi>Habit:</hi> for vvhereas man after his fall had onely a poſſibilitie to Belief, Faith does not onely reduce that poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity into an ability, but alſo into a facility. Though Chriſt lay a yoke upon us, Faith makes it eaſie: though Chriſt lay a burden on us, Faith makes it light; <hi>Draw me, we will run after thee,</hi> ſays the Spouſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. 4. Nor does this Faith teach onely to runne, but alſo it ſhews us, which way to runne: it does not onely give us vvill, but alſo knowledge, it being an habit of the underſtanding. And this is manifeſt from the act of Faith, which is, to believe: To believe, being an act of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which does notwithſtanding include an act of the will; the underſtanding in this act being determined by the command of the will; The act of believing being a cogitation with an aſſent, whereby eternal life is begun in us: This is the end, and yet the beginning of Faith, according to that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118893:12"/>of the Apoſtle, Faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for; the certainty of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by Faith being counted for poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And it gives this poſſeſſion, whiles it makes the underſtanding firmly aſſent, it makes it aſſent; it is the victory of the holy Ghoſt upon the underſtanding; which is happily led captive into liberty, and by the power of Grace is delivered from the bondage of Nature. And being delivered, it does firmly aſſent. There is a neutral act of the underſtanding, incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to neither part; and that is doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. There is an act of the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inclining onely to one part, but it is onely through ſome light reaſon, and that is conjecture. There is an act of the underſtanding, inclining likewiſe onely to one part, but it is with fear, and that is, Opinion: But this act of Faith is not onely to one part, but alſo with a firm aſſent. In which firmneſſe of aſſent it agrees with knowledge: from which, notwithſtanding it alſo diſagrees; knowledge being of things, that are manifeſt to the underſtanding; but Faith
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118893:13"/>being of things that do not appear. And thus is the act of Faith diſtinct from all the other acts of the underſtanding. Will you ſee the <hi>Power</hi> that <hi>produces</hi> Faith? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Grace, For ſince the object of Faith is above nature, the act of Faith muſt likewiſe be above nature: and therefore muſt proceed from ſuch a cauſe, as is able to raiſe the ſoul to ſuch an aſſent. Now whereas faith comes by knowledge, and knowledge ſeems to depend rather upon the induſtry of nature, then upon infuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: True it is, Faith does depend upon nature, in reſpect of its outward cauſe, as external perſuaſion; but the principal and proper cauſe of Faith is grace work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inwardly in the ſoul. Will yee ſee the <hi>excellency</hi> of Faith? You ſee it is a ſupernatural gift. It is above corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: which, alas, is ſo corrupt, that of it ſelf it is not onely not able to believe, but does ungraciouſly reſiſt belief. But was it alſo above <hi>Pure</hi> nature? had not our Parents, in the ſtate of Innocency, Faith? Faith they had in God; but had they Faith in <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Could <hi>Chriſt</hi> be the object of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118893:13"/>man's Faith, before man's fall? If we conſider the perſon of our Saviour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of God and Man; it were impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſay, he was then the object of Faith: but if we conſider the ſufficiency, which was radicated in the Divine Nature, and by which power the Divine Nature did aſſume the Humane Nature, we may ſay, that man could then believe in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe then he was able to believe in God, in what manner ſoever it ſhould pleaſe God to exhibit his ſufficiency; whether under the nature of Creation, Redemption, or Sanctification; Faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more properly grounded in the ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of theſe acts, then in the ſpecifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them. Gold, Chryſtal, and a Starre are the object of the fight, not in reſpect of ſolidity and tranſparency, but in reſpect of viſibility; in which they all agree. But a foreknowledge of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which implies mans fall, ſeems not congruous with the ſtate of Innocence; ſuch knowledge being not a degree of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection before man's fall, but a relief of his imperfection after it. Yet <hi>Aquinas</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutely,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118893:14"/>if not warrantably, thinks, that <hi>Adam</hi> then foreknew the myſtery of the Incarnation, though not as a means of Redemption, yet of mans perfection in the future viſion of God. Will you ſee the manner of the <hi>Production</hi> of Faith? It is wrought in the ſoul by a double work of grace; by an illumination of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and by an excitation of the will. Grace inlightens the underſtanding, whereby firſt it looks forward on the Law; and then it reflects upon its own guilt, and ſo begets Fear. Next it beholds eternal life, and a promiſe of that life in Chriſt. Grace likewiſe inflames the will, firſt to deſire remiſſion of ſinnes, and then an application of <hi>Chriſts</hi> promiſes to ones ſelf, for the effecting of ſuch remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Theſe then are the <hi>things,</hi> which grace makes us look after: this is the <hi>Order</hi> of the things, which grace makes us look after; the Law, the Goſpel, Pardon, and the Application of Pardon. Behold like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the <hi>Paſsions,</hi> which grace makes us feel: Behold, the <hi>Order</hi> of the Paſſions, which grace makes us feel: Fear, Hope,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118893:14"/>Deſire, Joy. This is the Method of the holy Ghoſt in the converſion of the Soul. And as ſome of theſe degrees goe before faith, ſo you may ſee alſo the <hi>degrees</hi> of faith. You ſhall ſometimes ſee a faith ſo weak, that it appears to be rather Deſire, then Faith. But yet it is a deſire not only of ſalvation, (for <hi>Balaam</hi> alſo could deſire to die the death of the Righteous:) but it is alſo a deſire of Righteouſneſs. The fool &amp; the wiſe man both deſire the end; but only the wiſe man deſires alſo the means. Now this deſire of grace is never without grace, and has the promiſe of bleſſedneſſe. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they that hunger and thirſt after righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> (<hi>Mat.</hi> 5.6.) And though this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Faith be not Faith, (Deſire being a Paſſion, and Faith an Habit) yet this deſire of Faith is never without Faith, it is an infallible effect of Faith. The deſire of grace is a ſanctified affection; and where one affection is ſanctified, all are ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and where all are ſanctified, the whole man is ſanctified. He likewiſe that is ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, is juſtified; and he that is juſtified, believes. He then that unfeignedly deſires
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118893:15"/>Faith, has Faith: Which deſire proceeds not from a want of Faith, but from a want of the knowledge of Faith; divers having Faith, but not the skill to know it. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times you ſhall finde the weakneſs of Faith in reſpect of knowledge, the knowledge of the Goſpel. Thus was the Apoſtles Faith in the knowledge of our Saviours Death and Reſurrection. For when our Saviour told them of his going down to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and his ſufferings there, <hi>Peter</hi> rebukes him, and ſayes, Maſter have pity on thy ſelf; this ſhall not be unto thee. Sometimes you ſhall finde the weakneſſe of Faith in the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion or application of Chriſt's benefits to our ſelves. Yet even ſuch Faith, ſuch palſie-Faith, is able to receive a gift from Chriſt; it is able to take hold on <hi>Chriſt;</hi> who has compaſſionately promiſed not to <hi>break the bruiſed reed;</hi> no, nor to quench <hi>the ſmoaking flax.</hi> But at laſt our obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall finde a ſtrength of Faith; you ſhall feel a ſtrength of Faith. A yong faith is but a tender faith; but a grown faith is a ſtrong faith; it grows, as the body does, from Infancy to Age. Which ſtrength of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118893:15"/>faith ariſes from a continual obſervation of God's ſecret favours and motions in the ſoul, through the whole courſe of life in the employments of the ſoul. And yet this ſtrength of faith is imperfect in this life, the wiſdome of God having left ſome doubtings in man, that he may remember he is but man, that he may the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly depend upon the merits of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, God and Man. And thus by a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious art, he makes us by fearing the ſtrength of our faith, to increaſe the ſtrength of it; he ſhews his ſtrength in our weakneſs; nay, he makes his ſtrength our ſtrength. And (to ſee the <hi>Effects</hi> of faith) as there is no ground ſo weak, but will by manuring, if it has any heart in it, beare ſome grain; ſo Faith, though weak, being true Faith, has ſome heart in it, and will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly bear ſome fruit: The infallible fruit of Faith, as the Apoſtle teaches us, is a good conſcience. Faith is the cauſe, and a good conſcience the effect; whoſe evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence depending upon the cauſe, makes it inſeparable. And ſince a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is never without charity, we may by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118893:16"/>the degrees of our charity meaſure the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of our faith; and by a want of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity diſcern a want of faith. And ſince a good conſcience is a continual Feaſt; there is proviſion not onely for him that makes the Feaſt, There is proviſion enough not onely wherewith to pleaſe himſelf, but wherwith alſo to pleaſe God. As then faith provides a good conſcience; ſo a good conſcience always provides a Sacrifice for God. Look upon <hi>Abel's Sacrifice,</hi> which the Lord did look upon; and you ſhall ſee <hi>why</hi> the Lord did look upon it. Both <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Cain</hi> offered that which was required, they offer'd it to God, by whom it was required: but only <hi>Abel</hi> offer'd all that was required. <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> in a ſeeming holineſs ſold their poſſeſſions. This was an action in it ſelf indifferent; in pretence, good; in purpoſe, bad; yea, vile: whileſt they ſold not onely their poſſeſſions, but alſo them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to work wickedneſs. For when they brought the money to the Apoſtles, as a full offering, the price of all, they kept back a part: ſo when <hi>Cain</hi> brought his offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the Lord, hee kept back a part.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118893:16"/>
               <hi>Nam Cain cum Deo offerret ſua, ſeip ſum ſibi retinuerat,</hi> ſays <hi>Rupertus.</hi> Hee brought an offering to God, but hee left his heart behinde him. Hee could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in God; but thought, that as God had no need of our offerings, ſo he had no regard of our offerings. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, he had no regard of his offering; nay, therefore God had no regard of it, becauſe <hi>Cain</hi> would not believe that God would regard it. But <hi>Abel</hi> firſt brought his heart, and then the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of his flock. His ſacrifice was not only an offering from his flock, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo from his conſcience. He did believe, that he that commanded ſacrifice, did therefore regard it, becauſe he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it. He did believe, God could not command that which was unjuſt; he could not command that which was in vain: Therefore he had regard to offer ſacrifice, becauſe he believed God did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>You may ſee in <hi>Abel</hi> the whole courſe of <hi>Faith.</hi> He did both <hi>know</hi> Gods will, and <hi>aſſent</hi> unto it, and <hi>profeſſed</hi> both, by
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118893:17"/>his ſacrifice he brought: nay, he <hi>rejoyced and brought forth fruit,</hi> whiles he brought for ſacrifice the fruit of his flock. He went yet higher; his faith was <hi>a faith of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles;</hi> for his faith fetch'd fire from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to conſume the ſacrifice of his faith. Nay, this faith of <hi>miracles</hi> was alſo a <hi>ſaving faith:</hi> it was the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of what he hoped for; he hoped to enjoy God in the Heavens, and by <hi>Faith</hi> he <hi>prevents</hi> that joy, and has him here on earth. His Faith was the <hi>Evidence</hi> of God, whom he hoped to ſee; and by his Faith he ſaw God in the <hi>fire</hi> of his ſacrifice. In which fire that deſcended to conſume a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, the <hi>Rabbines</hi> have a tradition, that the face of a Lion did ſtill appear, to repreſent the Lion of the tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> (which to us is our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi>) by whoſe only mediation ſacrifices are made acceptable. <hi>Abel's</hi> Faith was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo an <hi>habit,</hi> by which his ſacrifice was made as acceptable as it was willing and ready; and he as freely yielded it to the Lord, as his flock yielded it to him. And this offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118893:17"/>of Faith proceeded both from his underſtanding and his will; the fire ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd as much, which did not only <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> his <hi>ſacrifice</hi> made by Faith, but alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt the <hi>nature</hi> of the <hi>Faith:</hi> the light ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed his knowledge, and the heat his love. The cauſe was Grace: <hi>Adam</hi> could inſtruct him to offer by Faith; but <hi>Adam</hi> could not enable him to offer by Faith: the knowledge was from <hi>Adam,</hi> but the power from God. And though his faith was before ours, yet the manner of the <hi>production</hi> of it was like ours. He under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the high offence of his Father, and how that nature had caſt him likewiſe under the ſame guilt; this taught him to <hi>fear:</hi> he had likewiſe heard of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, that <hi>the ſeed of the Woman ſhould break the Serpents head:</hi> this made him to <hi>hope;</hi> and both theſe inflam'd his <hi>deſire</hi> to apply thoſe mercies to himſelf. The next degree of his faith, was the <hi>wiſdom</hi> of his faith: which was to uſe thoſe <hi>means,</hi> which might attain the end. <hi>Cain</hi> no doubt, wiſh'd Heaven as much as <hi>Abel,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:118893:18"/>but not as well: <hi>Cain</hi> deſir'd Heaven, but not Righteouſneſs; but <hi>Abel</hi> deſired Righteouſneſs, as heartily as he deſired Heaven. This made his ſacrifice as acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable unto God, as Heaven was acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable unto <hi>Abel.</hi> Now the reaſon why faith is of all virtues ſo acceptable unto God, is, becauſe God is moſt honoured by faith: for by faith we truſt God, we take God's Word; and ſo at once ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge in him <hi>ſufficiency</hi> and <hi>truth:</hi> ſufficiency, that he is able to perform unto us what hee does promiſe; and truth, that he will infallibly perform it. Thus did faithful <hi>Abraham</hi> honour God, when upon Gods promiſe he left his Countrey, his plentiful Countrey, and his kindred, not regarding the cenſures of the worldly-wiſe, even in that age of the world, who were ready to interpret his travail a levity and indiſcretion, to leave things certain for that which ſeemed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain. Yet he did arm himſelf with Divine Wiſdome againſt Humane wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, againſt falſe diſcretion, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118893:18"/>his eye upon the danger, but upon the command; which hee did not exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, but ſpeedily execute. This was the faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi> whom God hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. But <hi>Abel</hi> was an example both for us and for <hi>Abraham;</hi> if not for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of his faith, yet for the precedency of it: which as God made for an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the beginning of the world, ſo he intended it for an example to the end of the world. Since then we have ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent an hope in God, and ſo excellent an example in <hi>Abel:</hi> ſince God ſo looked upon his ſacrifice, that we might look upon his Faith: ſince <hi>Abel's</hi> Faith was more precious unto God, then his blood, Let us beg of God, that he will give us as true a Faith, though not as glorious a Faith, as <hi>Abels:</hi> that he will give us not only the knowledge of faith, but alſo the comfort of it, a good conſcience: that he will make our Heart the Sacrifice, and his Grace the Fire, both to reſtifie his love unto us, and to inflame our love unto him; and that we may ſo follow <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> in Faith, that we may follow him in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118893:19"/>Happineſſe. Which God grant for the merits of the blood of <hi>Jeſus, which ſpeaks better things then the blood of Abel;</hi> and work it for us by the power of his holy Spirit, the giver of all good gifts, the giver of Faith. To which Three Perſons and one God, bee all faithful Sacrifice of Thanks and Praiſe, now and for ever.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:118893:19"/>
            <head>Emendations.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAg.</hi> 4. <hi>lin.</hi> 1. <hi>dele</hi> hee. <hi>Pag.</hi> 5. <hi>lin.</hi> 11. and 12. <hi>read</hi> of corruption by the grave and death. <hi>Pag.</hi> 8. <hi>lin.</hi> 10. for underſtand, <hi>r.</hi> underſtood. <hi>P.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 4. for <hi>Theodoſian, r. Theodotion. Pag.</hi> 14. <hi>lin. ult.</hi> for continue, <hi>read</hi> convince. <hi>P.</hi> 26. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>dele</hi> was, and for faith, <hi>r.</hi> fail'd. <hi>P.</hi> 27. <hi>l.</hi> 3, 4. for evidence, <hi>r.</hi> exiſtence.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
